Hi man, welcome.
Hey, great to be here.
Yeah, where are you joining us from?
Tel Aviv.
Oh man, so it's a little late there. I
imagine.
Yeah, 10:00 p.m.
Oh man.
I have my coffee, so I think I'm fine.
Good, good. Yes, I've been doing the
same to keep me going here as well.
Thank you so much for joining us at this
time.
Maybe you can uh
uh clarify the question that Simon asked
at the end where where where the term
open LLM telemetry I can't even say it
came from originally.
Yeah, it's true. It's it's from Patrick.
He asked on Twitter like it was 2 weeks
before we were were about to release the
open source. He asked like waiting for
open LLM entry.
And and we didn't have a name. We just
called it like our SDK or something like
Facebook SDK. And then we I saw this
tweet and I was like, okay, this is a
this is a really good name. I know that
no one will be able to pronounce it, but
everyone will understand, you know, what
Yeah.
product is based on and what is it
supposed to be doing.
Yes, that's awesome. Well, thanks so
much for taking the time to join us here
to tell us all about all of this good
stuff and how the world of LLM and
observability can come together. So,
with that, I'm going to leave the stage
and hand it all over to you.
Thank you.
Uh yes, I'm going to talk a bit about
open telemetry and open LLM entry and
how they all fit together. And
wanted to uh talk a bit about how it all
connects to agents observability because
I know we've been talking a little bit
about agents today.
Um so, let's let's dive in.
Uh
great.
So, yeah, we're going to talk about
OpenTelemetry
today, but I think
to understand, you know, what
OpenTelemetry is, I think maybe it's
it's it's worth, you know, talking a
little bit about the origins of
OpenTelemetry or like the technology
that's that's been
driving and and been underlying
OpenTelemetry, which is, you know,
OpenTelemetry.
And so, OpenTelemetry, in case you
you've never heard about it, it's one of
the largest projects maintained by the
CNCF. It's an open source project, and
CNCF is is part of the Linux Foundation.
And it's currently supported by all the
major observability platforms that is
out there are out there. So, you know,
I'm showing you some logos like Splunk,
Datadog, Dynatrace, New Relic,
Honeycomb, Grafana, and there's like
many, many others. So, when if you're
using OpenTelemetry, you can basically
easily connect it to any
any of these platform and like
easily switch between them.
But, what what does not as OpenTelemetry
means exactly?
So, OpenTelemetry is a protocol. It's a
way for production It's a way for you to
do observability on production
applications. Remember, we're not in the
LLM generative AI agents world yet.
We're talking about a protocol that was
started uh
you know,
5-6 years ago, and and and and was
originally developed for just regular
cloud observability.
And the OpenTelemetry specification
contains three different types of things
you can kind of observe.
Logging, metrics, and tracing.
Logging, I think, is the most common
one. It's
Everyone knows about logging, right? You
have written, you know, a print or
console.log on on TypeScript, you've
done logging. So, these are if I'm
trying to like define it, so logging is
basically some just sending arbitrary
events that just happened in the system.
And if I'm
going to talk a bit about how does
logging looks like for agents or
generative AI based applications, I'm
talking about maybe logging the prompts
or logging the completions or logging
function calls. So, these are you know,
huge blobs of text if we just want to
log and know that they happen and and
and see, you know, state the exact
content.
Next up is metrics. Metrics are
things that you collect, so data points
you collect and that you usually want to
look look at them on on an aggregate
level and on like different time time
frames.
So, again taking into the, you know,
generative AI world we're talking about
token usage, latencies, error rates,
things like that.
And lastly we have tracing. I think
tracing, unless you've worked on like
multi
multi microservices architectures, you
you you can't
you're not used to thinking about
tracing, but tracing is super common
when you have you know, systems with
complex flows. Let's say you have like a
multiple microservice architecture and
you have like, you know, requests going
on going through uh many of them,
then then tracing really makes sense.
And and to be honest, OpenTelemetry
actually started with tracing and only
then
advanced towards metrics and and
logs.
And so, tracing is tracking of tracking
of multi multi-step processes.
And again taking into the LLM world,
we're thinking about, you know,
chains on LangChain or full executions
of agents, we're thinking about things
that have like multi-step processes, and
we want to see, you know,
details about each step, and we want to
see the whole process. So, that have
like a nice graphic here of like a rag
bag, and so I want to see, you know,
I want to see how much the whole
pipeline took, but I want to see each
individual individual steps, and I also
may want to see some details about each
step. If there's like a retrieval step,
I want to see what happened here there,
what was retrieved from from the
database, and and if I have a call to
like open AI, I want to see that call, I
want to see what happened there. So,
there's like a, you know, a combination
of looking at the overall process and
looking at individual steps.
Yeah, logging metrics and tracing, this
is the basis of of Open Telemetry.
Uh but, Open Telemetry is not just
defining a protocol, it's defining a
full ecosystem.
Uh Open Telemetry has a
set of many many different SDKs, and I
don't know if I have a slide here.
Uh Open Telemetry has
uh many different SDKs supporting many
languages. So, if you have, you know,
code written in Python or TypeScript or
Go or C++ or a lot of different
languages,
you have you can just install the SDK of
Open Telemetry, and you can, you know,
you can use it for logging metrics and
traces.
Um
but, it doesn't stop there. Open
Telemetry builds these packages called
instrumentations. So, you know, let's
say you want to get
logs
whenever you're querying your database,
then uh you can, you know, you can just
write yourself, call the Open Telemetry
SDK API, and like log what you want to
log, but you also have some built-in
instrumentations that do this for you
automatically. So, if you use the
Postgres uh
uh instrumentation, then you just get it
out of the box. You use them with the
my secret instrumentation again, you
just get some, you know,
logs and some metrics and some traces.
Just out of the box.
So, it's pretty cool. So, imagine, you
know, you want to use OpenTelemetry, you
install the SDK, you install a couple of
instrumentations, and you get lot of
information and visibility into what's
happening in your system just just in in
under 2 minutes.
The last thing that OpenTelemetry has is
uh
Yeah, and I have
That seems OpenTelemetry has, sorry, is
I was looking if I have a specific slide
on the instrumentations and collectors.
Uh the last thing we have in
OpenTelemetry is collectors. And
collectors is a way for you to do some
post-processing to the data that you
send out. And it has some advanced
features which you may need if you, for
example, want to send the data the
observability data to, you know,
multiple destinations. You want to see
the data in Datadog and in Honeycomb as
well. So, you want to use a collector
which aggregates data and send it out to
multiple sinks.
Or if you want to filter out some data,
you want to scrub out like PII, then you
can use a collector.
Uh the good thing about everything that
I mentioned is that everything is open
source. So,
if you're not using OpenTelemetry today,
just you can just start using it. It's
completely free and it connects to
whatever you're using.
Um
So, instrumentations. I talked about I
talked a bit about it before. The idea
is that you have, you know,
uh
you have
an SDK of that's using like Postgres,
and then if you install the
OpenTelemetry instrumentation for
Postgres, then it monkey patches into
that SDK, so it looks into the different
methods within that SDK and like logs
and and everything that is needed.
Everything happens on application side,
so we get the complete visibility into
what's happening in system.
And collectors, yeah, I also I already
talked about it, I think.
We can leave it in there.
We can leave it at it.
Okay, I think I think we covered, you
know, enough ground to to begin talking
about
Open LLM entry.
So, Open Open LLM entry is the project
that we've built. We started building it
about a week about a year ago.
And we've decided to take, you know, the
Open Telemetry instrument Open Telemetry
ecosystem and extend it to support
generative AI,
LLMs, agents,
and everything in between.
And so, we've built instrumentations for
the Open AI SDK,
and also, you know, many, many others.
Anthropic, Bedrock, Chroma, Pinecone.
There's I think more than 40 different
frameworks providers that are supported
today within Open Telemetry.
And
And if you remember, you know,
instrumentation is basically just
connecting monkey patching some SDK,
like the Open AI SDK, and it and sending
out logs, metrics, and traces
automatically whenever you do any action
with that SDK.
So, then what you get is that you you
instrument all these libraries, and then
you can send it out to whatever platform
you want.
And it's easy, you know, if you want to
send it to Datadog, you just set up some
environment variables or configure the
collector, and you send it there. You
find You want to send it to something
else, to Sentry, to Grafana, you just do
some configuration change, and that's
it. Everything is super standard.
So, it's pretty cool.
So, within Open Telemetry, we've built
instrumentations for basically all the
foundation models and providers that are
out there.
And we've built some of them in
collaboration with these providers, like
the Bedrock and Gemini.
And some of them are just monkey
patching these SDKs.
Uh
we have vector databases support, so
Pinecone, then many others. And there's
also support for frameworks like
LangChain, LlamaIndex, and Haystack.
Everything is open source, so you can
easily extend it, you can easily use it,
and you can
and it's relying on OpenTelemetry.
Uh, I feel like I'm saying OpenTelemetry
so many times these these last 20
minutes.
Uh, here's an example of the Pinecone
instrumentation just to give you a sense
of what you can get, you know, just by
installing this instrumentation. So,
Pinecone is a vector database vector
database for those of you who doesn't
who don't know that. And
it's commonly used if you building if
you're building a RAG pipeline. So, if
you're building a pipeline that's
you know, querying uh,
you have like let's say a user asking a
question and you want to answer that
question giving some context, giving
some context that you you have and you
indexed yourself on Pinecone. So, the
flow is that you get a question from the
user, you query the database, you get
some context that may answer the
question, then using an LLM to take the
context and the question and and answer
the question.
And so, for the Pinecone
instrumentation, we log all the queries,
all the indexes that are happening
within Pinecone,
and then also all the vector data vector
details that are returned.
And we also log
all sorts of metrics that give you sense
of like latencies and the different
scores that the vector databases are
providing you.
So, it's it's pretty cool.
I think
we have
it's it's about time to to for me to
stop just showing you slides and talking
and maybe show you a quick demo that can
give you a sense of what's
what's exactly am I talking about.
And I'm going to go to my IDE,
and I'll build this nice, you know,
make it a bit larger cuz I think
otherwise might be a bit small.
But, I'll build here, you know, a small
demo. I built it with LangChain.
And it's an agent.
And it's an agent that has one tool. It
uses the the really search results that
can search the web. And so, we use
OpenAI.
And we use the tool. And then we just
execute the agent using LangGraph.
And then, you know, further down the
line, super simple, we just send it out
like a question. I'm
I'm I'm Bob. I'm calling from somewhere,
so let's just change to I'm Near because
I'm not Bob. I'm Near.
And I don't live in Tel Aviv. I live in
Tel Aviv.
And yeah, I want to know what's the
weather.
So, so this is it. And we're going to
run it in a bit. Just before we run it,
we run it, we want to just want to show
you how you you how you want to use Open
LLM Entry. So, you have many things
happening here. You have, you know,
LangChain, you have OpenAI. And and all
of it is supported by the Open LLM Entry
SDK. So, what we do is we just add, you
know, these two lines.
And that's it. Once we add these two
lines, and of course I installed the SDK
by running poetry add or pip install
tracer-sdk.
And that's it. Once I did Once I've done
that,
I'm instrumenting OpenAI and LangChain
and everything in between. And I can
just, you know, run the application and
and see everything that happened behind
the scenes. So, let's do that.
Okay. I'm going to run it.
There we go.
And it's probably take a few seconds,
and I'm going to get an answer. And I'm
guessing you might be too small for you
to see, but yeah, I got an answer saying
uh
it executed the tool and
uh and it gave me and it gave me some
answer. Great.
Oh, and I was wondering why it gave me
an answer about San Francisco, but I can
just sort of I forgot to save the file.
So, just because I really want to know
the weather in Tel Aviv, I'm going to
run it again. So, give it another 2
seconds.
Let's see if I can increase the font in
the meantime.
Should be all right.
Okay.
Cool. So, I got the answer. Currently in
Tel Aviv, the weather is clear with a
temperature of 18.1°
C. Oh, it's it's a bit colder than I
thought.
Uh
cool. So, it's it's really nice. It's an
agent. It ran
um
you know, it ran
a bunch of calls to to open AI and then
it ran the tool. So, you know, we got a
uh
we've got a nice
we've got an we've got an answer like
using the tool. So, it's it's a nice
agent execution. But, I think you know,
just looking at this
it's kind of messy. I'm not sure if I
completely understand what happened here
behind the scenes. So, I think the the
thing that trace might make a bit more
sense.
So, let's see how the trace looks like.
And yeah, so yeah, 10:21. This is from
now. Let's look at the uh trace. So,
you can see here a lot of things
happened behind the scenes for me to get
an answer to uh to the question of you
know, what
what's the weather like in Tel Aviv
right now.
And as you can see, you can easily see,
you know, the different
steps that took place within that uh
LangGraph execution. You have an agent
call, you have a tool call, and as you
can see, I actually called the tool. And
I can see that the query was current
weather in Tel Aviv, which sounds like
something that should be done through a
search. And then I can also see the
output. I can see the result of the
tool. I got some JSON here with some
data from weather API.
And I'm guessing that at some point this
went to, yeah, check Open AI and use all
this information. And then
uh
I'm guessing that, yeah, it looks like
Open AI returned that currently in Tel
Aviv, the weather is clear with a
temperature of 18.5. So,
I think this give this give you a sense
of, you know, why looking at a trace can
make much more sense than just looking
at some uh
stream of, you know, log events.
And so, this is this is the basic idea
of around like, you know, why
open using Open Telemetry to to to do
observability for uh
for LLMs will make sense. We've got to
see here, you know, everything that's
happening in the system. We've got to
see the calls to Open AI. We've got to
see, you know, the agent execution, the
the tool call. And so, it it it really
can help us understand what happens uh
behind the scenes. So, if you can't
compare this to the messy logs that we
had here.
I think it I think it's clear, you know,
what's what's better. Uh and and and the
best thing, and I think this is what the
Open Telemetry protocol is is all about,
is is that everything is sent in a
standard format. So, you know, if you
want to use that standard format and
build other tools on top of it to do,
you know, better visualizations of the
agent execution like a graph or
something like that, then it's easy for
you to do it. You just
look at the specification of how how
these uh uh
agents are working, and you just build
on top of it.
Uh sorry, how how the Open Telemetry is
working, you just build on top of it.
So, yeah, that's it. It's
pretty cool. And if you have any
questions or anything, then uh now it's
a good time to ask them.
Awesome. Thank you so much for
teaching us about that and then showing
it um
uh through the demo. So, um have you
noticed uh any patterns yourselves or
yourself around
um things like
different responsiveness for different
providers, different, you know, models,
like these kind of things? Like are you
able to see kind of some of the
like meta
uh pieces on top of this and and do you
see customers that use that as a way to
kind of test and like do the kind of the
evaluation on the performance side of
these different models, providers, and
the like?
Yeah, definitely. Because, you know, you
get metrics at latency, so it's easy for
you to just, you know, run things in
parallel and compare uh
data. And and also I would say it's not
just it it's giving you more details
into what's happening behind the scenes.
Like one of the things that we
discovered,
there's a
there's a a a field, for example, on
OpenAI called a fingerprint, which tells
you kind of like the what's the system
that was used
for running your your your prompt. And
it it can change pretty often. And it's
kind of can be like a bit surprising.
And just, you know, by observing it, you
know, when is it changing? And so, you
often hear people saying like, "Hey, I
think I feel like for always is a bit is
less smart this week than it was last
week."
Many of the times this is the reason.
Like they they're using They've
they've changed something in the system.
And and it's not like a new model or
something. It's just if you look at the
fingerprint, you'll see different
fingerprint. And this will tell you,
"Okay, something has changed in the
internal architecture."
Got it. That's really interesting. And
then I assume around also testing out
just different token lengths and playing
around with all of those things to kind
of try and hit the sweet spot of
you know,
messing with quality and latency and
performance.
Yeah, exactly. And and I really like the
fact that, you know, I like open-source
projects, I like open protocols. I think
being able to,
you know, get the freedom of using
whatever you you're feeling comfortable
with and is is a huge, you know, it's a
huge benefit when when you want to
choose which tool you want to use.
Got it. Uh
are there any future things in the in
the protocol or in Trace Loop itself
that you're you're excited about getting
to?
I think agents
I we've talked about agents, but I
think, you know, being able to better
visualize agents execution is something
that I'm really excited about as like we
see
we started to see I think people have
been talking about agents for a long
time, but now we're starting to see more
and more
agents use in production. So, I think
being able to build better
visualizations on top of just basic
tracing that we saw today will be super
useful as we get to see more
and more of these actually running and
serving customers and users.
Got it. That makes sense.
Yeah, and then I've been thinking about
just, you know, as
you have these different agent
frameworks and being able to build
different graphs and lang lang graph and
the like, um
and then seeing reasoning tokens and
things being put into the LLMs
themselves,
like it can be a tricky to write like
when do I kind of sit on top of the LLMs
and poke it and do chain of thought and
do all of these things versus like the
LLMs are all changing at the same time.
Right.
Yeah, I'm curious to see what
how this all kind of evolves and plays
out and how I can use this kind of
telemetry to kind of help me as I'm
evolving while the whole ecosystem is
evolving.
Yeah, and I think you know, the more
things we get that sometimes you get
Open AI think in the past year they kind
of
uh added a lot of capabilities to their
models kind of like extending what on on
top of like the bare bone, you know, LLM
actual LLM they have like a lot of
things happening around it and then
like, you know, they had like a JSON
schemas and and then assistants. And so
I hope that it will it will at some
point you will also get some
visibility to what's happening there
because if that doesn't work and and
can't happen, you know,
being able to debug, you know, what went
wrong inside cuz maybe it was some into
the dice and
can be a super helpful.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Uh Uneeb has a question here. How shall
I approach integrating
um Open LLM Metry in a code base that
already has normal open telemetry
instrumentation?
It's a great question. Um
I think uh
you it shouldn't it shouldn't really
matter because the Open LLM Metry
if if you go to the GitHub repo then
you'll see it's basically it contains uh
all the the instrumentations as a
separate packages. So you have like Open
AI and Tropic and and if you already
using Open Telemetry you can just take
the individual
uh
instrumentations and just install them
and it will work. Uh all of them work
with like the Open Telemetry auto
instrumentation. So if you're using Open
Telemetry and and you know and you
already have it integrated then just
uh installing the instrumentations
directly work.
Otherwise, I think we've built like the
wrapper that I've shown in the demo like
the two lines install because a lot of
people
don't know how to install Open Telemetry
and we we wanted to bridge that gap of
like installing and configuring Open
Telemetry.
Got it. Sounds good. Okay. Do you have
any any final thoughts for the
community?
Um
yeah, I think
welcome everyone to like uh join, you
know, the
discussions around the open source. And
if anyone has any
uh anyone wants to contribute, you know,
more options uh more more
instrumentations, then we'll we'd love
that. Uh we've been working closely, you
know, between our community, the open
telemetry community, we've been
collaborating closely. And um
yeah, we'd
always uh love to have more uh
folks join our open source community.
Right. Thank you so much. Thank you for
taking the time to share all of this
again with it being so late where you
are, too. It's really appreciated. And
uh look forward to seeing you on the
Discord and continuing the conversation.
Yeah, it was great uh great being here.
Thank you.
Great. Cheers.
Bye.